Name

glBindAttribLocation — associate a generic vertex attribute index with a named attribute variable

C Specification

void glBindAttribLocation( | GLuint program,
  | GLuint index,
  | const GLchar *name);

Parameters

program

Specifies the handle of the program object in which the association is to be made.

index

Specifies the index of the generic vertex attribute to be bound.

name

Specifies a null terminated string containing the name of the vertex shader attribute variable to which index is to be bound.

Description

glBindAttribLocation is used to associate a user-defined attribute variable in the program object specified by program with a generic vertex attribute index. The name of the user-defined attribute variable is passed as a null terminated string in name. The generic vertex attribute index to be bound to this variable is specified by index. When program is made part of current state, values provided via the generic vertex attribute index will modify the value of the user-defined attribute variable specified by name.

If name refers to a matrix attribute variable, index refers to the first column of the matrix. Other matrix columns are then automatically bound to locations index+1 for a matrix of type mat2; index+1 and index+2 for a matrix of type mat3; and index+1, index+2, and index+3 for a matrix of type mat4.

This command makes it possible for vertex shaders to use descriptive names for attribute variables rather than generic variables that are numbered from 0 to GL_MAX_VERTEX_ATTRIBS -1. The values sent to each generic attribute index are part of current state, just like standard vertex attributes such as color, normal, and vertex position. If a different program object is made current by calling glUseProgram, the generic vertex attributes are tracked in such a way that the same values will be observed by attributes in the new program object that are also bound to index.

Attribute variable name-to-generic attribute index bindings for a program object can be explicitly assigned at any time by calling glBindAttribLocation. Attribute bindings do not go into effect until glLinkProgram is called. After a program object has been linked successfully, the index values for generic attributes remain fixed (and their values can be queried) until the next link command occurs.

Applications are not allowed to bind any of the standard OpenGL vertex attributes using this command, as they are bound automatically when needed. Any attribute binding that occurs after the program object has been linked will not take effect until the next time the program object is linked.

Notes

glBindAttribLocation can be called before any vertex shader objects are bound to the specified program object. It is also permissible to bind a generic attribute index to an attribute variable name that is never used in a vertex shader.

If name was bound previously, that information is lost. Thus you cannot bind one user-defined attribute variable to multiple indices, but you can bind multiple user-defined attribute variables to the same index.

Applications are allowed to bind more than one user-defined attribute variable to the same generic vertex attribute index. This is called aliasing, and it is allowed only if just one of the aliased attributes is active in the executable program, or if no path through the shader consumes more than one attribute of a set of attributes aliased to the same location. The compiler and linker are allowed to assume that no aliasing is done and are free to employ optimizations that work only in the absence of aliasing. OpenGL implementations are not required to do error checking to detect aliasing. Because there is no way to bind standard attributes, it is not possible to alias generic attributes with conventional ones (except for generic attribute 0).

Active attributes that are not explicitly bound will be bound by the linker when glLinkProgram is called. The locations assigned can be queried by calling glGetAttribLocation.

OpenGL copies the name string when glBindAttribLocation is called, so an application may free its copy of the name string immediately after the function returns.

Errors

GL_INVALID_VALUE is generated if index is greater than or equal to GL_MAX_VERTEX_ATTRIBS.

GL_INVALID_OPERATION is generated if name starts with the reserved prefix "gl_".

GL_INVALID_VALUE is generated if program is not a value generated by OpenGL.

GL_INVALID_OPERATION is generated if program is not a program object.

Associated Gets

glGet with argument GL_MAX_VERTEX_ATTRIBS

glGetActiveAttrib with argument program

glGetAttribLocation with arguments program and name

glIsProgram

{$pipelinestall}{$examples}

See Also

glDisableVertexAttribArray, glEnableVertexAttribArray, glUseProgram, glVertexAttrib, glVertexAttribPointer

Copyright

Copyright © 2003-2005 3Dlabs Inc. Ltd. This material may be distributed subject to the terms and conditions set forth in the Open Publication License, v 1.0, 8 June 1999. https://opencontent.org/openpub/.

Name

glBindBuffer — bind a named buffer object

C Specification

void glBindBuffer( | GLenum target,
  | GLuint buffer);

Parameters

target

Specifies the target to which the buffer object is bound. The symbolic constant must be GL_ARRAY_BUFFER or GL_ELEMENT_ARRAY_BUFFER.

buffer

Specifies the name of a buffer object.

Description

glBindBuffer lets you create or use a named buffer object. Calling glBindBuffer with target set to GL_ARRAY_BUFFER or GL_ELEMENT_ARRAY_BUFFER and buffer set to the name of the new buffer object binds the buffer object name to the target. When a buffer object is bound to a target, the previous binding for that target is automatically broken.

Buffer object names are unsigned integers. The value zero is reserved, but there is no default buffer object for each buffer object target. Instead, buffer set to zero effectively unbinds any buffer object previously bound, and restores client memory usage for that buffer object target. Buffer object names and the corresponding buffer object contents are local to the shared object space of the current GL rendering context.

You may use glGenBuffers to generate a set of new buffer object names.

The state of a buffer object immediately after it is first bound is a zero-sized memory buffer with GL_STATIC_DRAW usage.

While a non-zero buffer object name is bound, GL operations on the target to which it is bound affect the bound buffer object, and queries of the target to which it is bound return state from the bound buffer object. While buffer object name zero is bound, as in the initial state, attempts to modify or query state on the target to which it is bound generates an GL_INVALID_OPERATION error.

When vertex array pointer state is changed by a call to glVertexAttribPointer, the current buffer object binding (GL_ARRAY_BUFFER_BINDING) is copied into the corresponding client state for the vertex attrib array being changed, one of the indexed GL_VERTEX_ATTRIB_ARRAY_BUFFER_BINDINGs. While a non-zero buffer object is bound to the GL_ARRAY_BUFFER target, the vertex array pointer parameter that is traditionally interpreted as a pointer to client-side memory is instead interpreted as an offset within the buffer object measured in basic machine units.

While a non-zero buffer object is bound to the GL_ELEMENT_ARRAY_BUFFER target, the indices parameter of glDrawElements that is traditionally interpreted as a pointer to client-side memory is instead interpreted as an offset within the buffer object measured in basic machine units.

A buffer object binding created with glBindBuffer remains active until a different buffer object name is bound to the same target, or until the bound buffer object is deleted with glDeleteBuffers.

Once created, a named buffer object may be re-bound to any target as often as needed. However, the GL implementation may make choices about how to optimize the storage of a buffer object based on its initial binding target.

Errors

GL_INVALID_ENUM is generated if target is not one of the allowable values.

Associated Gets

glGet with argument GL_ARRAY_BUFFER_BINDING

glGet with argument GL_ELEMENT_ARRAY_BUFFER_BINDING

{$pipelinestall}{$examples}

See Also

glDeleteBuffers, glGenBuffers, glGet, glIsBuffer

Copyright

Copyright © 2005 Addison-Wesley. This material may be distributed subject to the terms and conditions set forth in the Open Publication License, v 1.0, 8 June 1999. https://opencontent.org/openpub/.

Name

glBindFramebuffer — bind a named framebuffer object

C Specification

void glBindFramebuffer( | GLenum target,
  | GLuint framebuffer);

Parameters

target

Specifies the target to which the framebuffer object is bound. The symbolic constant must be GL_FRAMEBUFFER.

framebuffer

Specifies the name of a framebuffer object.

Description

glBindFramebuffer lets you create or use a named framebuffer object. Calling glBindFramebuffer with target set to GL_FRAMEBUFFER and framebuffer set to the name of the new framebuffer object binds the framebuffer object name. When a framebuffer object is bound, the previous binding is automatically broken.

Framebuffer object names are unsigned integers. The value zero is reserved to represent the default framebuffer provided by the windowing system. Framebuffer object names and the corresponding framebuffer object contents are local to the shared object space of the current GL rendering context.

You may use glGenFramebuffers to generate a set of new framebuffer object names.

The state of a framebuffer object immediately after it is first bound is three attachment points (GL_COLOR_ATTACHMENT0, GL_DEPTH_ATTACHMENT, and GL_STENCIL_ATTACHMENT) each with GL_NONE as the object type.

While a non-zero framebuffer object name is bound, GL operations on target GL_FRAMEBUFFER affect the bound framebuffer object, and queries of target GL_FRAMEBUFFER or of framebuffer details such as GL_DEPTH_BITS return state from the bound framebuffer object. While framebuffer object name zero is bound, as in the initial state, attempts to modify or query state on target GL_FRAMEBUFFER generates an GL_INVALID_OPERATION error.

While a non-zero framebuffer object name is bound, all rendering to the framebuffer (with glDrawArrays and glDrawElements) and reading from the framebuffer (with glReadPixels, glCopyTexImage2D, or glCopyTexSubImage2D) use the images attached to the application-created framebuffer object rather than the default window-system-provided framebuffer.

Application created framebuffer objects (i.e. those with a non-zero name) differ from the default window-system-provided framebuffer in a few important ways. First, they have modifiable attachment points for a color buffer, a depth buffer, and a stencil buffer to which framebuffer attachable images may be attached and detached. Second, the size and format of the attached images are controlled entirely within the GL and are not affected by window-system events, such as pixel format selection, window resizes, and display mode changes. Third, when rendering to or reading from an application created framebuffer object, the pixel ownership test always succeeds (i.e. they own all their pixels). Fourth, there are no visible color buffer bitplanes, only a single "off-screen" color image attachment, so there is no sense of front and back buffers or swapping. Finally, there is no multisample buffer, so the value of the implementation-dependent state variables GL_SAMPLES and GL_SAMPLE_BUFFERS are both zero for application created framebuffer objects.

A framebuffer object binding created with glBindFramebuffer remains active until a different framebuffer object name is bound, or until the bound framebuffer object is deleted with glDeleteFramebuffers.

Notes

Queries of implementation-dependent pixel depths and related state are derived from the currently bound framebuffer object. These include GL_RED_BITS, GL_GREEN_BITS, GL_BLUE_BITS, GL_ALPHA_BITS, GL_DEPTH_BITS, GL_STENCIL_BITS, GL_IMPLEMENTATION_COLOR_READ_TYPE, GL_IMPLEMENTATION_COLOR_READ_FORMAT, GL_SAMPLES, and GL_SAMPLE_BUFFERS.

Errors

GL_INVALID_ENUM is generated if target is not GL_FRAMEBUFFER.

Associated Gets

glGet with argument GL_FRAMEBUFFER_BINDING

{$pipelinestall}{$examples}

See Also

glDeleteFramebuffers, glFramebufferRenderbuffer, glFramebufferTexture2D, glGenFramebuffers, glGet, glGetFramebufferAttachmentParameteriv, glIsFramebuffer

Copyright

Copyright © 2008 Khronos Group. This material may be distributed subject to the terms and conditions set forth in the Open Publication License, v 1.0, 8 June 1999. https://opencontent.org/openpub/.

Name

glBindRenderbuffer — bind a named renderbuffer object

C Specification

void glBindRenderbuffer( | GLenum target,
  | GLuint renderbuffer);

Parameters

target

Specifies the target to which the renderbuffer object is bound. The symbolic constant must be GL_RENDERBUFFER.

renderbuffer

Specifies the name of a renderbuffer object.

Description

A renderbuffer is a data storage object containing a single image of a renderable internal format. A renderbuffer's image may be attached to a framebuffer object to use as a destination for rendering and as a source for reading.

glBindRenderbuffer lets you create or use a named renderbuffer object. Calling glBindRenderbuffer with target set to GL_RENDERBUFFER and renderbuffer set to the name of the new renderbuffer object binds the renderbuffer object name. When a renderbuffer object is bound, the previous binding is automatically broken.

Renderbuffer object names are unsigned integers. The value zero is reserved, but there is no default renderbuffer object. Instead, renderbuffer set to zero effectively unbinds any renderbuffer object previously bound. Renderbuffer object names and the corresponding renderbuffer object contents are local to the shared object space of the current GL rendering context.

You may use glGenRenderbuffers to generate a set of new renderbuffer object names.

The state of a renderbuffer object immediately after it is first bound is a zero-sized memory buffer with format GL_RGBA4 and zero-sized red, green, blue, alpha, depth, and stencil pixel depths.

While a non-zero renderbuffer object name is bound, GL operations on target GL_RENDERBUFFER affect the bound renderbuffer object, and queries of target GL_RENDERBUFFER return state from the bound renderbuffer object. While renderbuffer object name zero is bound, as in the initial state, attempts to modify or query state on target GL_RENDERBUFFER generates an GL_INVALID_OPERATION error.

A renderbuffer object binding created with glBindRenderbuffer remains active until a different renderbuffer object name is bound, or until the bound renderbuffer object is deleted with glDeleteRenderbuffers.

Errors

GL_INVALID_ENUM is generated if target is not GL_RENDERBUFFER.

Associated Gets

glGet with argument GL_RENDERBUFFER_BINDING

{$pipelinestall}{$examples}

See Also

glDeleteRenderbuffers, glFramebufferRenderbuffer, glGenRenderbuffers, glGet, glGetRenderbufferParameteriv, glIsRenderbuffer, glRenderbufferStorage

Copyright

Copyright © 2008 Khronos Group. This material may be distributed subject to the terms and conditions set forth in the Open Publication License, v 1.0, 8 June 1999. https://opencontent.org/openpub/.

Name

glCheckFramebufferStatus — return the framebuffer completeness status of a framebuffer object

C Specification

GLenum glCheckFramebufferStatus( | GLenum target);

Parameters

target

Specifies the target framebuffer object. The symbolic constant must be GL_FRAMEBUFFER.

Description

glCheckFramebufferStatus returns a symbolic constant that identifies whether or not the currently bound framebuffer is framebuffer complete, and if not, which of the rules of framebuffer completeness is violated.

If the framebuffer is complete, then GL_FRAMEBUFFER_COMPLETE is returned. If the framebuffer is not complete, the return values are as follows:

GL_FRAMEBUFFER_INCOMPLETE_ATTACHMENT

Not all framebuffer attachment points are framebuffer attachment complete. This means that at least one attachment point with a renderbuffer or texture attached has its attached object no longer in existence or has an attached image with a width or height of zero, or the color attachment point has a non-color-renderable image attached, or the depth attachment point has a non-depth-renderable image attached, or the stencil attachment point has a non-stencil-renderable image attached.

Color-renderable formats include GL_RGBA4, GL_RGB5_A1, and GL_RGB565. GL_DEPTH_COMPONENT16 is the only depth-renderable format. GL_STENCIL_INDEX8 is the only stencil-renderable format.

GL_FRAMEBUFFER_INCOMPLETE_DIMENSIONS

Not all attached images have the same width and height.

GL_FRAMEBUFFER_INCOMPLETE_MISSING_ATTACHMENT

No images are attached to the framebuffer.

GL_FRAMEBUFFER_UNSUPPORTED

The combination of internal formats of the attached images violates an implementation-dependent set of restrictions.

If the currently bound framebuffer is not framebuffer complete, then it is an error to attempt to use the framebuffer for writing or reading. This means that rendering commands (glClear, glDrawArrays, and glDrawElements) as well as commands that read the framebuffer (glReadPixels, glCopyTexImage2D, and glCopyTexSubImage2D) will generate the error GL_INVALID_FRAMEBUFFER_OPERATION if called while the framebuffer is not framebuffer complete.

Notes

It is strongly advised, thought not required, that an application call glCheckFramebufferStatus to see if the framebuffer is complete prior to rendering. This is because some implementations may not support rendering to particular combinations of internal formats. In this case, GL_FRAMEBUFFER_UNSUPPORTED is returned.

The default window-system-provided framebuffer is always framebuffer complete, and thus GL_FRAMEBUFFER_COMPLETE is returned when GL_FRAMEBUFFER_BINDING is 0.

Additionally, if an error occurs, zero is returned.

Errors

GL_INVALID_ENUM is generated if target is not GL_FRAMEBUFFER.

{$pipelinestall}{$examples}

See Also

glBindRenderbuffer, glCopyTexImage2D, glCopyTexSubImage2D, glDrawArrays, glDrawElements, glReadPixels, glRenderbufferStorage

Copyright

Copyright © 2008 Khronos Group. This material may be distributed subject to the terms and conditions set forth in the Open Publication License, v 1.0, 8 June 1999. https://opencontent.org/openpub/.

Name

glCreateShader — create a shader object

C Specification

GLuint glCreateShader( | GLenum shaderType);

Parameters

shaderType

Specifies the type of shader to be created. Must be either GL_VERTEX_SHADER or GL_FRAGMENT_SHADER.

Description

glCreateShader creates an empty shader object and returns a non-zero value by which it can be referenced. A shader object is used to maintain the source code strings that define a shader. shaderType indicates the type of shader to be created. Two types of shaders are supported. A shader of type GL_VERTEX_SHADER is a shader that is intended to run on the programmable vertex processor. A shader of type GL_FRAGMENT_SHADER is a shader that is intended to run on the programmable fragment processor.

When created, a shader object's GL_SHADER_TYPE parameter is set to either GL_VERTEX_SHADER or GL_FRAGMENT_SHADER, depending on the value of shaderType.

Notes

Like texture objects, the name space for shader objects may be shared across a set of contexts, as long as the server sides of the contexts share the same address space. If the name space is shared across contexts, any attached objects and the data associated with those attached objects are shared as well.

Applications are responsible for providing the synchronization across API calls when objects are accessed from different execution threads.

Errors

This function returns 0 if an error occurs creating the shader object.

GL_INVALID_ENUM is generated if shaderType is not an accepted value.

Associated Gets

glGetShaderiv with a valid shader object and the parameter to be queried

glGetShaderInfoLog with a valid shader object

glGetShaderSource with a valid shader object

glIsShader

{$pipelinestall}{$examples}

See Also

glAttachShader, glCompileShader, glDeleteShader, glDetachShader, glShaderSource, glShaderBinary

Copyright

Copyright © 2003-2005 3Dlabs Inc. Ltd. This material may be distributed subject to the terms and conditions set forth in the Open Publication License, v 1.0, 8 June 1999. https://opencontent.org/openpub/.

Name

glDeleteRenderbuffers — delete named renderbuffer objects

C Specification

void glDeleteRenderbuffers( | GLsizei n,
  | const GLuint * renderbuffers);

Parameters

n

Specifies the number of renderbuffer objects to be deleted.

renderbuffers

Specifies an array of renderbuffer objects to be deleted.

Description

glDeleteRenderbuffers deletes n renderbuffer objects named by the elements of the array renderbuffers. After a renderbuffer object is deleted, it has no contents, and its name is free for reuse (for example by glGenRenderbuffers).

If a renderbuffer object that is currently bound is deleted, the binding reverts to 0 (the absence of any renderbuffer object). Additionally, special care must be taken when deleting a renderbuffer object if the image of the renderbuffer is attached to a framebuffer object. In this case, if the deleted renderbuffer object is attached to the currently bound framebuffer object, it is automatically detached. However, attachments to any other framebuffer objects are the responsibility of the application.

glDeleteRenderbuffers silently ignores 0's and names that do not correspond to existing renderbuffer objects.

Errors

GL_INVALID_VALUE is generated if n is negative.

Associated Gets

glIsRenderbuffer

{$pipelinestall}{$examples}

See Also

glBindRenderbuffer, glGenRenderbuffers, glIsRenderbuffer

Copyright

Copyright © 2008 Khronos Group. This material may be distributed subject to the terms and conditions set forth in the Open Publication License, v 1.0, 8 June 1999. https://opencontent.org/openpub/.

Name

glFramebufferRenderbuffer — attach a renderbuffer object to a framebuffer object

C Specification

void glFramebufferRenderbuffer( | GLenum target,
  | GLenum attachment,
  | GLenum renderbuffertarget,
  | GLuint renderbuffer);

Parameters

target

Specifies the framebuffer target. The symbolic constant must be GL_FRAMEBUFFER.

attachment

Specifies the attachment point to which renderbuffer should be attached. Must be one of the following symbolic constants: GL_COLOR_ATTACHMENT0, GL_DEPTH_ATTACHMENT, or GL_STENCIL_ATTACHMENT.

renderbuffertarget

Specifies the renderbuffer target. The symbolic constant must be GL_RENDERBUFFER.

renderbuffer

Specifies the renderbuffer object that is to be attached.

Description

glFramebufferRenderbuffer attaches the renderbuffer specified by renderbuffer as one of the logical buffers of the currently bound framebuffer object. attachment specifies whether the renderbuffer should be attached to the framebuffer object's color, depth, or stencil buffer. A renderbuffer may not be attached to the default framebuffer object name 0.

If renderbuffer is not 0, the value of GL_FRAMEBUFFER_ATTACHMENT_OBJECT_TYPE for the specified attachment point is set to GL_RENDERBUFFER and the value of GL_FRAMEBUFFER_ATTACHMENT_OBJECT_NAME is set to renderbuffer. GL_FRAMEBUFFER_ATTACHMENT_TEXTURE_LEVEL and GL_FRAMEBUFFER_ATTACHMENT_TEXTURE_CUBE_MAP_FACE are set to the default values 0 and GL_TEXTURE_CUBE_MAP_POSITIVE_X, respectively. Any previous attachment to the attachment logical buffer of the currently bound framebuffer object is broken.

If renderbuffer is 0, the current image, if any, attached to the attachment logical buffer of the currently bound framebuffer object is detached. The value of GL_FRAMEBUFFER_ATTACHMENT_OBJECT_TYPE is set to GL_NONE. The value of GL_FRAMEBUFFER_ATTACHMENT_OBJECT_NAME is set to 0. GL_FRAMEBUFFER_ATTACHMENT_TEXTURE_LEVEL and GL_FRAMEBUFFER_ATTACHMENT_TEXTURE_CUBE_MAP_FACE are set to the default values 0 and GL_TEXTURE_CUBE_MAP_POSITIVE_X, respectively.

Notes

If a renderbuffer object is deleted while its image is attached to the currently bound framebuffer, then it is as if glFramebufferRenderbuffer had been called with a renderbuffer of 0 for the attachment point to which this image was attached in the currently bound framebuffer object. In other words, the renderbuffer image is detached from the currently bound framebuffer. Note that the renderbuffer image is specifically not detached from any non-bound framebuffers. Detaching the image from any non-bound framebuffers is the responsibility of the application.

Errors

GL_INVALID_ENUM is generated if target is not GL_FRAMEBUFFER.

GL_INVALID_ENUM is generated if renderbuffertarget is not GL_RENDERBUFFER and renderbuffer is not 0.

GL_INVALID_ENUM is generated if attachment is not an accepted attachment point.

GL_INVALID_OPERATION is generated if the default framebuffer object name 0 is bound.

GL_INVALID_OPERATION is generated if renderbuffer is neither 0 nor the name of an existing renderbuffer object.

Associated Gets

glGetFramebufferAttachmentParameteriv

{$pipelinestall}{$examples}

See Also

glBindFramebuffer, glBindRenderbuffer, glCheckFramebufferStatus, glDeleteFramebuffers, glDeleteRenderbuffers, glFramebufferTexture2D, glGetFramebufferAttachmentParameteriv, glRenderbufferStorage

Copyright

Copyright © 2008 Khronos Group. This material may be distributed subject to the terms and conditions set forth in the Open Publication License, v 1.0, 8 June 1999. https://opencontent.org/openpub/.

Name

glFramebufferTexture2D — attach a texture image to a framebuffer object

C Specification

void glFramebufferTexture2D( | GLenum target,
  | GLenum attachment,
  | GLenum textarget,
  | GLuint texture,
  | GLint level);

Parameters

target

Specifies the framebuffer target. The symbolic constant must be GL_FRAMEBUFFER.

attachment

Specifies the attachment point to which an image from texture should be attached. Must be one of the following symbolic constants: GL_COLOR_ATTACHMENT0, GL_DEPTH_ATTACHMENT, or GL_STENCIL_ATTACHMENT.

textarget

Specifies the texture target. Must be one of the following symbolic constants: GL_TEXTURE_2D, GL_TEXTURE_CUBE_MAP_POSITIVE_X, GL_TEXTURE_CUBE_MAP_NEGATIVE_X, GL_TEXTURE_CUBE_MAP_POSITIVE_Y, GL_TEXTURE_CUBE_MAP_NEGATIVE_Y, GL_TEXTURE_CUBE_MAP_POSITIVE_Z, or GL_TEXTURE_CUBE_MAP_NEGATIVE_Z.

texture

Specifies the texture object whose image is to be attached.

level

Specifies the mipmap level of the texture image to be attached, which must be 0.

Description

glFramebufferTexture2D attaches the texture image specified by texture and level as one of the logical buffers of the currently bound framebuffer object. attachment specifies whether the texture image should be attached to the framebuffer object's color, depth, or stencil buffer. A texture image may not be attached to the default framebuffer object name 0.

If texture is not 0, the value of GL_FRAMEBUFFER_ATTACHMENT_OBJECT_TYPE for the specified attachment point is set to GL_TEXTURE, the value of GL_FRAMEBUFFER_ATTACHMENT_OBJECT_NAME is set to texture, and the value of GL_FRAMEBUFFER_ATTACHMENT_TEXTURE_LEVEL is set to level. If texture is a cube map texture, the value of GL_FRAMEBUFFER_ATTACHMENT_TEXTURE_CUBE_MAP_FACE is set to textarget; otherwise it is set to the default value GL_TEXTURE_CUBE_MAP_POSITIVE_X. Any previous attachment to the attachment logical buffer of the currently bound framebuffer object is broken.

If texture is 0, the current image, if any, attached to the attachment logical buffer of the currently bound framebuffer object is detached. The value of GL_FRAMEBUFFER_ATTACHMENT_OBJECT_TYPE is set to GL_NONE. The value of GL_FRAMEBUFFER_ATTACHMENT_OBJECT_NAME is set to 0. GL_FRAMEBUFFER_ATTACHMENT_TEXTURE_LEVEL and GL_FRAMEBUFFER_ATTACHMENT_TEXTURE_CUBE_MAP_FACE are set to the default values 0 and GL_TEXTURE_CUBE_MAP_POSITIVE_X, respectively.

Notes

Special precautions need to be taken to avoid attaching a texture image to the currently bound framebuffer while the texture object is currently bound and potentially sampled by the current vertex or fragment shader. Doing so could lead to the creation of a "feedback loop" between the writing of pixels by rendering operations and the simultaneous reading of those same pixels when used as texels in the currently bound texture. In this scenario, the framebuffer will be considered framebuffer complete, but the values of fragments rendered while in this state will be undefined. The values of texture samples may be undefined as well.

If a texture object is deleted while its image is attached to the currently bound framebuffer, then it is as if glFramebufferTexture2D had been called with a texture of 0 for the attachment point to which this image was attached in the currently bound framebuffer object. In other words, the texture image is detached from the currently bound framebuffer. Note that the texture image is specifically not detached from any non-bound framebuffers. Detaching the image from any non-bound framebuffers is the responsibility of the application.

Errors

GL_INVALID_ENUM is generated if target is not GL_FRAMEBUFFER.

GL_INVALID_ENUM is generated if textarget is not an accepted texture target and texture is not 0.

GL_INVALID_ENUM is generated if attachment is not an accepted attachment point.

GL_INVALID_VALUE is generated if level is not 0 and texture is not 0.

GL_INVALID_OPERATION is generated if the default framebuffer object name 0 is bound.

GL_INVALID_OPERATION is generated if texture is neither 0 nor the name of an existing texture object.

GL_INVALID_OPERATION is generated if texture is the name of an existing two-dimensional texture object but textarget is not GL_TEXTURE_2D or if texture is the name of an existing cube map texture object but textarget is GL_TEXTURE_2D.

Associated Gets

glGetFramebufferAttachmentParameteriv

{$pipelinestall}{$examples}

See Also

glBindFramebuffer, glBindTexture, glCheckFramebufferStatus, glDeleteFramebuffers, glDeleteTextures, glFramebufferRenderbuffer, glGenerateMipmap, glGetFramebufferAttachmentParameteriv, glTexImage2D

Copyright

Copyright © 2008 Khronos Group. This material may be distributed subject to the terms and conditions set forth in the Open Publication License, v 1.0, 8 June 1999. https://opencontent.org/openpub/.

Name

glGenerateMipmap — generate a complete set of mipmaps for a texture object

C Specification

void glGenerateMipmap( | GLenum target);

Parameters

target

Specifies the texture target of the active texture unit to which the texture object is bound whose mipmaps will be generated. Must be one of the following symbolic constants: GL_TEXTURE_2D or GL_TEXTURE_CUBE_MAP.

Description

glGenerateMipmap computes a complete set of mipmap arrays derived from the zero level array. Array levels up to and including the 1x1 dimension texture image are replaced with the derived arrays, regardless of previous contents. The zero level texture image is left unchanged.

The internal formats of the derived mipmap arrays all match those of the zero level texture image. The dimensions of the derived arrays are computed by halving the width and height of the zero level texture image, then in turn halving the dimensions of each array level until the 1x1 dimension texture image is reached.

The contents of the derived arrays are computed by repeated filtered reduction of the zero level array. No particular filter algorithm is required, though a box filter is recommended. glHint may be called to express a preference for speed or quality of filtering.

Errors

GL_INVALID_ENUM is generated if target is not GL_TEXTURE_2D or GL_TEXTURE_CUBE_MAP.

GL_INVALID_OPERATION is generated if the texture bound to target is a cube map, but its six faces do not share indentical widths, heights, formats, and types.

GL_INVALID_OPERATION is generated if either the width or height of the zero level array is not a power of two.

GL_INVALID_OPERATION is generated if the zero level array is stored in a compressed internal format.

{$pipelinestall}{$examples}

See Also

glBindTexture, glFramebufferTexture2D, glHint, glTexImage2D, glTexParameter

Copyright

Copyright © 2008 Khronos Group. This material may be distributed subject to the terms and conditions set forth in the Open Publication License, v 1.0, 8 June 1999. https://opencontent.org/openpub/.

Name

glGetFramebufferAttachmentParameteriv — return attachment parameters of a framebuffer object

C Specification

void glGetFramebufferAttachmentParameteriv( | GLenum target,
  | GLenum attachment,
  | GLenum pname,
  | GLint * params);

Parameters

target

Specifies the target framebuffer object. The symbolic constant must be GL_FRAMEBUFFER.

attachment

Specifies the symbolic name of a framebuffer object attachment point. Accepted values are GL_COLOR_ATTACHMENT0, GL_DEPTH_ATTACHMENT, and GL_STENCIL_ATTACHMENT.

pname

Specifies the symbolic name of a framebuffer object attachment parameter. Accepted values are GL_FRAMEBUFFER_ATTACHMENT_OBJECT_TYPE, GL_FRAMEBUFFER_ATTACHMENT_OBJECT_NAME, GL_FRAMEBUFFER_ATTACHMENT_TEXTURE_LEVEL, and GL_FRAMEBUFFER_ATTACHMENT_TEXTURE_CUBE_MAP_FACE.

params

Returns the requested parameter.

Description

glGetFramebufferAttachmentParameteriv returns in params a selected attachment parameter of the attachpoint point attachment of the currently bound framebuffer object.

pname names a specific framebuffer object attachment parameter, as follows:

GL_FRAMEBUFFER_ATTACHMENT_OBJECT_TYPE

params returns the type of object which contains the attached image, either GL_RENDERBUFFER, GL_TEXTURE, or if no image is attached, GL_NONE. The initial value is GL_NONE.

GL_FRAMEBUFFER_ATTACHMENT_OBJECT_NAME

If the value of GL_FRAMEBUFFER_ATTACHMENT_OBJECT_TYPE is GL_RENDERBUFFER, params returns the name of the renderbuffer object which contains the attached image. If the value of GL_FRAMEBUFFER_ATTACHMENT_OBJECT_TYPE is GL_TEXTURE, params returns the name of the texture object which contains the attached image. The initial value is zero.

GL_FRAMEBUFFER_ATTACHMENT_TEXTURE_LEVEL

If the value of GL_FRAMEBUFFER_ATTACHMENT_OBJECT_TYPE is GL_TEXTURE, params returns the mipmap level of the texture object which contains the attached image. The initial value is zero.

GL_FRAMEBUFFER_ATTACHMENT_TEXTURE_CUBE_MAP_FACE

If the value of GL_FRAMEBUFFER_ATTACHMENT_OBJECT_TYPE is GL_TEXTURE and GL_FRAMEBUFFER_ATTACHMENT_OBJECT_NAME is the name of a cube-map texture, params returns the cube map face of the cube-map texture object which contains the attached image. If the attached image is from a texture object but not a cube-map, params returns 0. The initial value is GL_TEXTURE_CUBE_MAP_POSITIVE_X.

Notes

If an error is generated, no change is made to the contents of params.

Errors

GL_INVALID_ENUM is generated if target is not GL_FRAMEBUFFER.

GL_INVALID_ENUM is generated if attachment is not GL_COLOR_ATTACHMENT0, GL_DEPTH_ATTACHMENT, or GL_STENCIL_ATTACHMENT.

GL_INVALID_ENUM is generated if the attached object at the named attachment point is GL_RENDERBUFFER and pname is not GL_FRAMEBUFFER_ATTACHMENT_OBJECT_TYPE or GL_FRAMEBUFFER_ATTACHMENT_OBJECT_NAME.

GL_INVALID_ENUM is generated if the attached object at the named attachment point is GL_TEXTURE and pname is not GL_FRAMEBUFFER_ATTACHMENT_OBJECT_TYPE, GL_FRAMEBUFFER_ATTACHMENT_OBJECT_NAME, GL_FRAMEBUFFER_ATTACHMENT_TEXTURE_LEVEL, or GL_FRAMEBUFFER_ATTACHMENT_TEXTURE_CUBE_MAP_FACE.

GL_INVALID_ENUM is generated if there is no attached object at the named attachment point and pname is not GL_FRAMEBUFFER_ATTACHMENT_OBJECT_TYPE.

GL_INVALID_OPERATION is generated if the default framebuffer object name 0 is bound.

{$pipelinestall}{$examples}

See Also

glBindFramebuffer, glFramebufferRenderbuffer, glFramebufferTexture2D

Copyright

Copyright © 2008 Khronos Group. This material may be distributed subject to the terms and conditions set forth in the Open Publication License, v 1.0, 8 June 1999. https://opencontent.org/openpub/.

Name

glGetShaderInfoLog — return the information log for a shader object

C Specification

void glGetShaderInfoLog( | GLuint shader,
  | GLsizei maxLength,
  | GLsizei *length,
  | GLchar *infoLog);

Parameters

shader

Specifies the shader object whose information log is to be queried.

maxLength

Specifies the size of the character buffer for storing the returned information log.

length

Returns the length of the string returned in infoLog (excluding the null terminator).

infoLog

Specifies an array of characters that is used to return the information log.

Description

glGetShaderInfoLog returns the information log for the specified shader object. The information log for a shader object is modified when the shader is compiled. The string that is returned will be null terminated.

glGetShaderInfoLog returns in infoLog as much of the information log as it can, up to a maximum of maxLength characters. The number of characters actually returned, excluding the null termination character, is specified by length. If the length of the returned string is not required, a value of NULL can be passed in the length argument. The size of the buffer required to store the returned information log can be obtained by calling glGetShaderiv with the value GL_INFO_LOG_LENGTH.

The information log for a shader object is a string that may contain diagnostic messages, warning messages, and other information about the last compile operation. When a shader object is created, its information log will be a string of length 0.

Notes

The information log for a shader object is the OpenGL implementer's primary mechanism for conveying information about the compilation process. Therefore, the information log can be helpful to application developers during the development process, even when compilation is successful. Application developers should not expect different OpenGL implementations to produce identical information logs.

Errors

GL_INVALID_VALUE is generated if shader is not a value generated by OpenGL.

GL_INVALID_OPERATION is generated if shader is not a shader object.

GL_INVALID_VALUE is generated if maxLength is less than 0.

Associated Gets

glGetShaderiv with argument GL_INFO_LOG_LENGTH

glIsShader

{$pipelinestall}{$examples}

See Also

glCompileShader, glGetProgramInfoLog, glLinkProgram, glValidateProgram

Copyright

Copyright © 2003-2005 3Dlabs Inc. Ltd. This material may be distributed subject to the terms and conditions set forth in the Open Publication License, v 1.0, 8 June 1999. https://opencontent.org/openpub/.

Name

glGetVertexAttrib — return a generic vertex attribute parameter

C Specification

void glGetVertexAttribfv( | GLuint index,
  | GLenum pname,
  | GLfloat *params);

void glGetVertexAttribiv( | GLuint index,
  | GLenum pname,
  | GLint *params);

Parameters

index

Specifies the generic vertex attribute parameter to be queried.

pname

Specifies the symbolic name of the vertex attribute parameter to be queried. Accepted values are GL_VERTEX_ATTRIB_ARRAY_BUFFER_BINDING, GL_VERTEX_ATTRIB_ARRAY_ENABLED, GL_VERTEX_ATTRIB_ARRAY_SIZE, GL_VERTEX_ATTRIB_ARRAY_STRIDE, GL_VERTEX_ATTRIB_ARRAY_TYPE, GL_VERTEX_ATTRIB_ARRAY_NORMALIZED, or GL_CURRENT_VERTEX_ATTRIB.

params

Returns the requested data.

Description

glGetVertexAttrib returns in params the value of a generic vertex attribute parameter. The generic vertex attribute to be queried is specified by index, and the parameter to be queried is specified by pname.

The accepted parameter names are as follows:

GL_VERTEX_ATTRIB_ARRAY_BUFFER_BINDING

params returns a single value, the name of the buffer object currently bound to the binding point corresponding to generic vertex attribute array index. If no buffer object is bound, 0 is returned. The initial value is 0.

GL_VERTEX_ATTRIB_ARRAY_ENABLED

params returns a single value that is non-zero (true) if the vertex attribute array for index is enabled and 0 (false) if it is disabled. The initial value is GL_FALSE.

GL_VERTEX_ATTRIB_ARRAY_SIZE

params returns a single value, the size of the vertex attribute array for index. The size is the number of values for each element of the vertex attribute array, and it will be 1, 2, 3, or 4. The initial value is 4.

GL_VERTEX_ATTRIB_ARRAY_STRIDE

params returns a single value, the array stride for (number of bytes between successive elements in) the vertex attribute array for index. A value of 0 indicates that the array elements are stored sequentially in memory. The initial value is 0.

GL_VERTEX_ATTRIB_ARRAY_TYPE

params returns a single value, a symbolic constant indicating the array type for the vertex attribute array for index. Possible values are GL_BYTE, GL_UNSIGNED_BYTE, GL_SHORT, GL_UNSIGNED_SHORT, GL_FIXED, and GL_FLOAT. The initial value is GL_FLOAT.

GL_VERTEX_ATTRIB_ARRAY_NORMALIZED

params returns a single value that is non-zero (true) if fixed-point data types for the vertex attribute array indicated by index are normalized when they are converted to floating point, and 0 (false) otherwise. The initial value is GL_FALSE.

GL_CURRENT_VERTEX_ATTRIB

params returns four values that represent the current value for the generic vertex attribute specified by index. The initial value is (0,0,0,1).

All of the parameters except GL_CURRENT_VERTEX_ATTRIB represent client-side state.

Notes

If an error is generated, no change is made to the contents of params.

Errors

GL_INVALID_ENUM is generated if pname is not an accepted value.

GL_INVALID_VALUE is generated if index is greater than or equal to GL_MAX_VERTEX_ATTRIBS.

Associated Gets

glGet with argument GL_MAX_VERTEX_ATTRIBS

glGetVertexAttribPointerv with arguments index and GL_VERTEX_ATTRIB_ARRAY_POINTER

{$pipelinestall}{$examples}

See Also

glBindAttribLocation, glBindBuffer, glDisableVertexAttribArray, glEnableVertexAttribArray, glVertexAttrib, glVertexAttribPointer

Copyright

Copyright © 2003-2005 3Dlabs Inc. Ltd. This material may be distributed subject to the terms and conditions set forth in the Open Publication License, v 1.0, 8 June 1999. https://opencontent.org/openpub/.

Name

glLinkProgram — link a program object

C Specification

void glLinkProgram( | GLuint program);

Parameters

program

Specifies the handle of the program object to be linked.

Description

glLinkProgram links the program object specified by program. A shader object of type GL_VERTEX_SHADER attached to program is used to create an executable that will run on the programmable vertex processor. A shader object of type GL_FRAGMENT_SHADER attached to program is used to create an executable that will run on the programmable fragment processor.

The status of the link operation will be stored as part of the program object's state. This value will be set to GL_TRUE if the program object was linked without errors and is ready for use, and GL_FALSE otherwise. It can be queried by calling glGetProgramiv with arguments program and GL_LINK_STATUS.

As a result of a successful link operation, all active user-defined uniform variables belonging to program will be initialized to 0, and each of the program object's active uniform variables will be assigned a location that can be queried by calling glGetUniformLocation. Also, any active user-defined attribute variables that have not been bound to a generic vertex attribute index will be bound to one at this time.

Linking of a program object can fail for a number of reasons as specified in the OpenGL ES Shading Language Specification. The following lists some of the conditions that will cause a link error.

A vertex shader and a fragment shader are not both present in the program object.

The number of active attribute variables supported by the implementation has been exceeded.

The storage limit for uniform variables has been exceeded.

The number of active uniform variables supported by the implementation has been exceeded.

The main function is missing for the vertex shader or the fragment shader.

A varying variable actually used in the fragment shader is not declared in the same way (or is not declared at all) in the vertex shader.

A reference to a function or variable name is unresolved.

A shared global is declared with two different types or two different initial values.

One or more of the attached shader objects has not been successfully compiled (via glCompileShader) or loaded with a pre-compiled shader binary (via glShaderBinary).

Binding a generic attribute matrix caused some rows of the matrix to fall outside the allowed maximum of GL_MAX_VERTEX_ATTRIBS.

Not enough contiguous vertex attribute slots could be found to bind attribute matrices.

When a program object has been successfully linked, the program object can be made part of current state by calling glUseProgram. Whether or not the link operation was successful, the program object's information log will be overwritten. The information log can be retrieved by calling glGetProgramInfoLog.

glLinkProgram will also install the generated executables as part of the current rendering state if the link operation was successful and the specified program object is already currently in use as a result of a previous call to glUseProgram. If the program object currently in use is relinked unsuccessfully, its link status will be set to GL_FALSE , but the executables and associated state will remain part of the current state until a subsequent call to glUseProgram removes it from use. After it is removed from use, it cannot be made part of current state until it has been successfully relinked.

The program object's information log is updated and the program is generated at the time of the link operation. After the link operation, applications are free to modify attached shader objects, compile attached shader objects, detach shader objects, delete shader objects, and attach additional shader objects. None of these operations affects the information log or the program that is part of the program object.

Notes

If the link operation is unsuccessful, any information about a previous link operation on program is lost (i.e., a failed link does not restore the old state of program). Certain information can still be retrieved from program even after an unsuccessful link operation. See for instance glGetActiveAttrib and glGetActiveUniform.

Errors

GL_INVALID_VALUE is generated if program is not a value generated by OpenGL.

GL_INVALID_OPERATION is generated if program is not a program object.

Associated Gets

glGet with the argument GL_CURRENT_PROGRAM

glGetActiveAttrib with argument program and the index of an active attribute variable

glGetActiveUniform with argument program and the index of an active uniform variable

glGetAttachedShaders with argument program

glGetAttribLocation with argument program and an attribute variable name

glGetProgramiv with arguments program and GL_LINK_STATUS

glGetProgramInfoLog with argument program

glGetUniform with argument program and a uniform variable location

glGetUniformLocation with argument program and a uniform variable name

glIsProgram

{$pipelinestall}{$examples}

See Also

glAttachShader, glBindAttribLocation, glCompileShader, glShaderBinary, glCreateProgram, glDeleteProgram, glDetachShader, glUniform, glUseProgram, glValidateProgram

Copyright

Copyright © 2003-2005 3Dlabs Inc. Ltd. This material may be distributed subject to the terms and conditions set forth in the Open Publication License, v 1.0, 8 June 1999. https://opencontent.org/openpub/.

Name

glReleaseShaderCompiler — release resources allocated by the shader compiler

C Specification

void glReleaseShaderCompiler( | void);

Description

For implementations that support a shader compiler, glReleaseShaderCompiler frees resources allocated by the shader compiler. This is a hint from the application that additional shader compilations are unlikely to occur, at least for some period of time, and that the resources consumed by the shader compiler may be released and put to better use elsewhere.

However, if a call to glCompileShader is made after a call to glReleaseShaderCompiler, the shader compiler must be restored to service the compilation request as if glReleaseShaderCompiler had never been called.

Notes

Shader compiler support is optional, and thus must be queried before use by calling glGet with argument GL_SHADER_COMPILER. glShaderSource, glCompileShader, glGetShaderPrecisionFormat, and glReleaseShaderCompiler will each generate GL_INVALID_OPERATION on implementations that do not support a shader compiler. Such implementations instead offer the glShaderBinary alternative for supplying a pre-compiled shader binary.

Errors

GL_INVALID_OPERATION is generated if a shader compiler is not supported.

Associated Gets

glGet with argument GL_SHADER_COMPILER

{$pipelinestall}{$examples}

See Also

glCompileShader, glShaderSource

Copyright

Copyright © 2008 Khronos Group. This material may be distributed subject to the terms and conditions set forth in the Open Publication License, v 1.0, 8 June 1999. https://opencontent.org/openpub/.

Name

glRenderbufferStorage — create and initialize a renderbuffer object's data store

C Specification

void glRenderbufferStorage( | GLenum target,
  | GLenum internalformat,
  | GLsizei width,
  | GLsizei height);

Parameters

target

Specifies the renderbuffer target. The symbolic constant must be GL_RENDERBUFFER.

internalformat

Specifies the color-renderable, depth-renderable, or stencil-renderable format of the renderbuffer. Must be one of the following symbolic constants: GL_RGBA4, GL_RGB565, GL_RGB5_A1, GL_DEPTH_COMPONENT16, or GL_STENCIL_INDEX8.

width

Specifies the width of the renderbuffer in pixels.

height

Specifies the height of the renderbuffer in pixels.

Description

glRenderbufferStorage establishes the data storage, format, and dimensions of a renderbuffer object's image. Any existing data store for the renderbuffer is deleted and the contents of the new data store are undefined.

An implementation may vary its allocation of internal component resolution based on any glRenderbufferStorage parameter (except target), but the allocation and chosen internal format must not be a function of any other state and cannot be changed once they are established. The actual resolution in bits of each component of the allocated image can be queried with glGetRenderbufferParameteriv.

Errors

GL_INVALID_ENUM is generated if target is not GL_RENDERBUFFER.

GL_INVALID_ENUM is generated if internalformat is not an accepted format.

GL_INVALID_VALUE is generated if width or height is less than zero or greater than GL_MAX_RENDERBUFFER_SIZE.

GL_OUT_OF_MEMORY is generated if the implementation is unable to create a data store with the requested width and height.

GL_INVALID_OPERATION is generated if the reserved renderbuffer object name 0 is bound.

Associated Gets

glGetRenderbufferParameteriv

{$pipelinestall}{$examples}

See Also

glBindRenderbuffer, glDeleteRenderbuffers, glFramebufferRenderbuffer, glGenRenderbuffers, glGetRenderbufferParameteriv, glIsRenderbuffer

Copyright

Copyright © 2008 Khronos Group. This material may be distributed subject to the terms and conditions set forth in the Open Publication License, v 1.0, 8 June 1999. https://opencontent.org/openpub/.

Name

glShaderBinary — load a precompiled shader binary

C Specification

void glShaderBinary( | GLsizei n,
  | const GLuint *shaders,
  | GLenum binaryformat,
  | const void *binary,
  | GLsizei length);

Parameters

n

Specifies the number of shader object handles present in shaders.

shaders

Specifies a pointer to an array of shader object handles into which the shader binary will be loaded.

binaryformat

Specifies the shader binary format.

binary

Specifies a pointer to the shader binary data in client memory.

length

Specifies the length of the shader binary data in bytes.

Description

For implementations that support them, glShaderBinary loads precompiled shader binaries. shaders contains a list of n shader object handles. Each handle refers to a unique shader type (vertex shader or fragment shader). binary points to precompiled binary shader code in client memory, and binaryformat denotes the format of the pre-compiled code.

The binary image is decoded according to the extension specification defining the specified binaryformat. OpenGL ES defines no specific binary formats, but does provide a mechanism to obtain symbolic constants for such formats provided by extensions. The number of shader binary formats supported can be obtained by querying the value of GL_NUM_SHADER_BINARY_FORMATS. The list of specific binary formats supported can be obtained by querying the value of GL_SHADER_BINARY_FORMATS.

Depending on the types of the shader objects in shaders, glShaderBinary will individually load binary vertex or fragment shaders, or load an executable binary that contains an optimized pair of vertex and fragment shaders stored in the same binary.

If glShaderBinary fails, the old state of shader objects for which the binary was being loaded will not be restored.

Notes

Shader binary support is optional and thus must be queried before use by calling glGet with arguments GL_NUM_SHADER_BINARY_FORMATS and GL_SHADER_BINARY_FORMATS. glShaderBinary generates GL_INVALID_OPERATION on implementations that do not support any shader binary formats. Such implementations instead offer the glShaderSource alternative for supplying OpenGL ES Shading Language shader source for compilation.

If shader binary formats are supported, then an implementation may require that an optimized pair of vertex and fragment shader binaries that were compiled together to be specified to glLinkProgram. Not specifying an optimized pair my cause glLinkProgram to fail. Such a restriction, if it exists, will be documented in the extension specification defining binaryformat.

OpenGL copies the shader binary data when glShaderBinary is called, so an application may free its copy of the data immediately after the function returns.

Errors

GL_INVALID_ENUM is generated if binaryformat is not a supported format returned in GL_SHADER_BINARY_FORMATS.

GL_INVALID_VALUE is generated if any value in shaders is not a vlue generated by OpenGL.

GL_INVALID_VALUE is generated if the format of the data pointed to by binary does not match binaryformat.

GL_INVALID_VALUE is generated if n or length is negative.

GL_INVALID_OPERATION is generated if any value in shaders is not a shader object, or if there is more than one vertex shader object handle or more than one fragment shader object handle in shaders.

Associated Gets

glGet with arguments GL_NUM_SHADER_BINARY_FORMATS and GL_SHADER_BINARY_FORMATS

glIsShader

{$pipelinestall}{$examples}

See Also

glCreateShader, glDeleteShader, glLinkProgram

Copyright

Copyright © 2008 Khronos Group. This material may be distributed subject to the terms and conditions set forth in the Open Publication License, v 1.0, 8 June 1999. https://opencontent.org/openpub/.

Name

glShaderSource — replace the source code in a shader object

C Specification

void glShaderSource( | GLuint shader,
  | GLsizei count,
  | const GLchar * const *string,
  | const GLint *length);

Parameters

shader

Specifies the handle of the shader object whose source code is to be replaced.

count

Specifies the number of elements in the string and length arrays.

string

Specifies an array of pointers to strings containing the source code to be loaded into the shader.

length

Specifies an array of string lengths.

Description

For implementations that support a shader compiler, glShaderSource sets the source code in shader to the source code in the array of strings specified by string. Any source code previously stored in the shader object is completely replaced. The number of strings in the array is specified by count. If length is NULL, each string is assumed to be null terminated. If length is a value other than NULL, it points to an array containing a string length for each of the corresponding elements of string. Each element in the length array may contain the length of the corresponding string (the null character is not counted as part of the string length) or a value less than 0 to indicate that the string is null terminated. The source code strings are not scanned or parsed at this time; they are simply copied into the specified shader object.

Notes

Shader compiler support is optional, and thus must be queried before use by calling glGet with argument GL_SHADER_COMPILER. glShaderSource, glCompileShader, glGetShaderPrecisionFormat, and glReleaseShaderCompiler will each generate GL_INVALID_OPERATION on implementations that do not support a shader compiler. Such implementations instead offer the glShaderBinary alternative for supplying a pre-compiled shader binary.

OpenGL copies the shader source code strings when glShaderSource is called, so an application may free its copy of the source code strings immediately after the function returns.

Errors

GL_INVALID_OPERATION is generated if a shader compiler is not supported.

GL_INVALID_VALUE is generated if shader is not a value generated by OpenGL.

GL_INVALID_OPERATION is generated if shader is not a shader object.

GL_INVALID_VALUE is generated if count is less than 0.

Associated Gets

glGet with argument GL_SHADER_COMPILER

glGetShaderiv with arguments shader and GL_SHADER_SOURCE_LENGTH

glGetShaderSource with argument shader

glIsShader

{$pipelinestall}{$examples}

See Also

glCompileShader, glGetShaderPrecisionFormat, glCreateShader, glDeleteShader

Copyright

Copyright © 2003-2005 3Dlabs Inc. Ltd. This material may be distributed subject to the terms and conditions set forth in the Open Publication License, v 1.0, 8 June 1999. https://opencontent.org/openpub/.

Name

glUseProgram — install a program object as part of current rendering state

C Specification

void glUseProgram( | GLuint program);

Parameters

program

Specifies the handle of the program object whose executables are to be used as part of current rendering state.

Description

glUseProgram installs the program object specified by program as part of current rendering state. Executables for each stage are created in a program object by successfully attaching shader objects to it with glAttachShader, successfully compiling the shader objects with glCompileShader, and successfully linking the program object with glLinkProgram.

A program object will contain executables that will run on the vertex and fragment processors if it contains one shader object of type GL_VERTEX_SHADER and one shader object of type GL_FRAGMENT_SHADER that have both been successfully compiled and linked.

While a program object is in use, applications are free to modify attached shader objects, compile attached shader objects, attach shader objects, and detach or delete shader objects. None of these operations will affect the executables that are part of the current state. However, relinking the program object that is currently in use will install the program object as part of the current rendering state if the link operation was successful (see glLinkProgram ). If the program object currently in use is relinked unsuccessfully, its link status will be set to GL_FALSE, but the executables and associated state will remain part of the current state until a subsequent call to glUseProgram removes it from use. After it is removed from use, it cannot be made part of current state until it has been successfully relinked.

If program is 0, then the current rendering state refers to an invalid program object, and the results of vertex and fragment shader execution due to any glDrawArrays or glDrawElements commands are undefined.

Notes

Like texture objects and buffer objects, the name space for program objects may be shared across a set of contexts, as long as the server sides of the contexts share the same address space. If the name space is shared across contexts, any attached objects and the data associated with those attached objects are shared as well.

Applications are responsible for providing the synchronization across API calls when objects are accessed from different execution threads.

Errors

GL_INVALID_VALUE is generated if program is neither 0 nor a value generated by OpenGL.

GL_INVALID_OPERATION is generated if program is not a program object.

GL_INVALID_OPERATION is generated if program could not be made part of current state.

Associated Gets

glGet with the argument GL_CURRENT_PROGRAM

glGetActiveAttrib with a valid program object and the index of an active attribute variable

glGetActiveUniform with a valid program object and the index of an active uniform variable

glGetAttachedShaders with a valid program object

glGetAttribLocation with a valid program object and the name of an attribute variable

glGetProgramiv with a valid program object and the parameter to be queried

glGetProgramInfoLog with a valid program object

glGetUniform with a valid program object and the location of a uniform variable

glGetUniformLocation with a valid program object and the name of a uniform variable

glIsProgram

{$pipelinestall}{$examples}

See Also

glAttachShader, glBindAttribLocation, glCompileShader, glCreateProgram, glDeleteProgram, glDetachShader, glLinkProgram, glUniform, glValidateProgram, glVertexAttrib

Copyright

Copyright © 2003-2005 3Dlabs Inc. Ltd. This material may be distributed subject to the terms and conditions set forth in the Open Publication License, v 1.0, 8 June 1999. https://opencontent.org/openpub/.

Name

glVertexAttrib — specify the value of a generic vertex attribute

C Specification

void glVertexAttrib1f( | GLuint index,
  | GLfloat v0);

void glVertexAttrib2f( | GLuint index,
  | GLfloat v0,
  | GLfloat v1);

void glVertexAttrib3f( | GLuint index,
  | GLfloat v0,
  | GLfloat v1,
  | GLfloat v2);

void glVertexAttrib4f( | GLuint index,
  | GLfloat v0,
  | GLfloat v1,
  | GLfloat v2,
  | GLfloat v3);

Parameters

index

Specifies the index of the generic vertex attribute to be modified.

v0, v1, v2, v3

Specifies the new values to be used for the specified vertex attribute.

C Specification

void glVertexAttrib1fv( | GLuint index,
  | const GLfloat *v);

void glVertexAttrib2fv( | GLuint index,
  | const GLfloat *v);

void glVertexAttrib3fv( | GLuint index,
  | const GLfloat *v);

void glVertexAttrib4fv( | GLuint index,
  | const GLfloat *v);

Parameters

index

Specifies the index of the generic vertex attribute to be modified.

v

Specifies a pointer to an array of values to be used for the generic vertex attribute.

Description

The glVertexAttrib family of entry points allows an application to pass generic vertex attributes in numbered locations.

Generic attributes are defined as four-component values that are organized into an array. The first entry of this array is numbered 0, and the size of the array is specified by the implementation-dependent symbolic constant GL_MAX_VERTEX_ATTRIBS. Individual elements of this array can be modified with a glVertexAttrib call that specifies the index of the element to be modified and a value for that element.

These commands can be used to specify one, two, three, or all four components of the generic vertex attribute specified by index. A 1 in the name of the command indicates that only one value is passed, and it will be used to modify the first component of the generic vertex attribute. The second and third components will be set to 0, and the fourth component will be set to 1. Similarly, a 2 in the name of the command indicates that values are provided for the first two components, the third component will be set to 0, and the fourth component will be set to 1. A 3 in the name of the command indicates that values are provided for the first three components and the fourth component will be set to 1, whereas a 4 in the name indicates that values are provided for all four components.

The letter f indicates that the arguments are of type float. When v is appended to the name, the commands can take a pointer to an array of floats.

OpenGL ES Shading Language attribute variables are allowed to be of type mat2, mat3, or mat4. Attributes of these types may be loaded using the glVertexAttrib entry points. Matrices must be loaded into successive generic attribute slots in column major order, with one column of the matrix in each generic attribute slot.

A user-defined attribute variable declared in a vertex shader can be bound to a generic attribute index by calling glBindAttribLocation. This allows an application to use descriptive variable names in a vertex shader. A subsequent change to the specified generic vertex attribute will be immediately reflected as a change to the corresponding attribute variable in the vertex shader.

The binding between a generic vertex attribute index and a user-defined attribute variable in a vertex shader is part of the state of a program object, but the current value of the generic vertex attribute is not. The value of each generic vertex attribute is part of current state and it is maintained even if a different program object is used.

An application may freely modify generic vertex attributes that are not bound to a named vertex shader attribute variable. These values are simply maintained as part of current state and will not be accessed by the vertex shader. If a generic vertex attribute bound to an attribute variable in a vertex shader is not updated while the vertex shader is executing, the vertex shader will repeatedly use the current value for the generic vertex attribute.

Notes

It is possible for an application to bind more than one attribute name to the same generic vertex attribute index. This is referred to as aliasing, and it is allowed only if just one of the aliased attribute variables is active in the vertex shader, or if no path through the vertex shader consumes more than one of the attributes aliased to the same location. OpenGL implementations are not required to do error checking to detect aliasing, they are allowed to assume that aliasing will not occur, and they are allowed to employ optimizations that work only in the absence of aliasing.

Errors

GL_INVALID_VALUE is generated if index is greater than or equal to GL_MAX_VERTEX_ATTRIBS.

Associated Gets

glGet with the argument GL_CURRENT_PROGRAM

glGetActiveAttrib with argument program and the index of an active attribute variable

glGetAttribLocation with argument program and an attribute variable name

glGetVertexAttrib with arguments GL_CURRENT_VERTEX_ATTRIB and index

{$pipelinestall}{$examples}

See Also

glBindAttribLocation, glVertexAttribPointer

Copyright

Copyright © 2003-2005 3Dlabs Inc. Ltd. This material may be distributed subject to the terms and conditions set forth in the Open Publication License, v 1.0, 8 June 1999. https://opencontent.org/openpub/.

Name

glVertexAttribPointer — define an array of generic vertex attribute data

C Specification

void glVertexAttribPointer( | GLuint index,
  | GLint size,
  | GLenum type,
  | GLboolean normalized,
  | GLsizei stride,
  | const GLvoid * pointer);

Parameters

index

Specifies the index of the generic vertex attribute to be modified.

size

Specifies the number of components per generic vertex attribute. Must be 1, 2, 3, or 4. The initial value is 4.

type

Specifies the data type of each component in the array. Symbolic constants GL_BYTE, GL_UNSIGNED_BYTE, GL_SHORT, GL_UNSIGNED_SHORT, GL_FIXED, or GL_FLOAT are accepted. The initial value is GL_FLOAT.

normalized

Specifies whether fixed-point data values should be normalized (GL_TRUE) or converted directly as fixed-point values (GL_FALSE) when they are accessed.

stride

Specifies the byte offset between consecutive generic vertex attributes. If stride is 0, the generic vertex attributes are understood to be tightly packed in the array. The initial value is 0.

pointer

Specifies a pointer to the first component of the first generic vertex attribute in the array. The initial value is 0.

Description

glVertexAttribPointer specifies the location and data format of the array of generic vertex attributes at index index to use when rendering. size specifies the number of components per attribute and must be 1, 2, 3, or 4. type specifies the data type of each component, and stride specifies the byte stride from one attribute to the next, allowing vertices and attributes to be packed into a single array or stored in separate arrays. If set to GL_TRUE, normalized indicates that values stored in an integer format are to be mapped to the range [-1,1] (for signed values) or [0,1] (for unsigned values) when they are accessed and converted to floating point. Otherwise, values will be converted to floats directly without normalization.

If a non-zero named buffer object is bound to the GL_ARRAY_BUFFER target (see glBindBuffer) while a generic vertex attribute array is specified, pointer is treated as a byte offset into the buffer object's data store. Also, the buffer object binding (GL_ARRAY_BUFFER_BINDING) is saved as generic vertex attribute array client-side state (GL_VERTEX_ATTRIB_ARRAY_BUFFER_BINDING) for index index.

When a generic vertex attribute array is specified, size, type, normalized, stride, and pointer are saved as client-side state, in addition to the current vertex array buffer object binding.

To enable and disable a generic vertex attribute array, call glEnableVertexAttribArray and glDisableVertexAttribArray with index. If enabled, the generic vertex attribute array is used when glDrawArrays or glDrawElements is called.

Notes

Each generic vertex attribute array is initially disabled and isn't accessed when glDrawElements or glDrawArrays is called.

glVertexAttribPointer is typically implemented on the client side.

Errors

GL_INVALID_ENUM is generated if type is not an accepted value.

GL_INVALID_VALUE is generated if index is greater than or equal to GL_MAX_VERTEX_ATTRIBS.

GL_INVALID_VALUE is generated if size is not 1, 2, 3, or 4.

GL_INVALID_VALUE is generated if stride is negative.

Associated Gets

glGet with argument GL_MAX_VERTEX_ATTRIBS

glGetVertexAttrib with arguments index and GL_VERTEX_ATTRIB_ARRAY_ENABLED

glGetVertexAttrib with arguments index and GL_VERTEX_ATTRIB_ARRAY_SIZE

glGetVertexAttrib with arguments index and GL_VERTEX_ATTRIB_ARRAY_TYPE

glGetVertexAttrib with arguments index and GL_VERTEX_ATTRIB_ARRAY_NORMALIZED

glGetVertexAttrib with arguments index and GL_VERTEX_ATTRIB_ARRAY_STRIDE

glGetVertexAttrib with arguments index and GL_VERTEX_ATTRIB_ARRAY_BUFFER_BINDING

glGet with argument GL_ARRAY_BUFFER_BINDING

glGetVertexAttribPointerv with arguments index and GL_VERTEX_ATTRIB_ARRAY_POINTER

See Also

glBindAttribLocation, glBindBuffer, glDisableVertexAttribArray, glDrawArrays, glDrawElements, glEnableVertexAttribArray, glVertexAttrib

Copyright

Copyright © 2003-2005 3Dlabs Inc. Ltd. This material may be distributed subject to the terms and conditions set forth in the Open Publication License, v 1.0, 8 June 1999. https://opencontent.org/openpub/.